<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>lipids | Ann Von Holle</title>
    <link>https://ann-von-holle.github.io/tag/lipids/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://ann-von-holle.github.io/tag/lipids/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>lipids</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Mar 2018 13:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://ann-von-holle.github.io/images/icon_huf78cfa0514f34e3e45701546128c26c0_21162_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>lipids</title>
      <link>https://ann-von-holle.github.io/tag/lipids/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Infant Growth as an Effect Modifier of Genetic-Lipid Associations: Evidence From a Chilean Infancy Cohort</title>
      <link>https://ann-von-holle.github.io/poster/2018-aha/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Mar 2018 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ann-von-holle.github.io/poster/2018-aha/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Aim 2</title>
      <link>https://ann-von-holle.github.io/project/dissertation-aim2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ann-von-holle.github.io/project/dissertation-aim2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Currently in review at 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://academic.oup.com/aje/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;the American Journal of Epidemiology&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oral presentation at the American Heart Association Epi|Lifestyle 2018 meeting. Slides created in 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.overleaf.com/read/trzmrtksswxn&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Overleaf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Growth in early infancy is hypothesized to affect chronic disease risk factors later in life. To date, most reports draw on European ancestry cohorts with few repeated observations in early infancy. We investigated the association between infant growth from birth to 5 months and lipid levels in adolescents in a Hispanic/Latino cohort to determine if previous findings generalize to diverse study populations and to obtain more detailed growth estimates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Study design&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We characterized infant growth with monthly measures from birth to five months in males (n=311) and females (n=285) from the Santiago Longitudinal Study (SLS) using three metrics: weight (kg), length (cm) and weight-for-length (g/cm). Nonlinear mixed effects (SITAR) and latent growth mixture models (LGMM) were two approaches to estimate infant growth characteristics. Growth was the exposure and lipid levels at 17 years were the outcomes, including HDL-C, LDL-C, TG, and a TG:HDL-C ratio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Results&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We found a positive relationship between the SITAR length velocity parameter before six months of age and HDL-C levels in adolescence (11.5, SE=4.1) indicating higher HDL-C levels occurring with faster length growth. The strongest associations from the LGMM models were between higher LDL-C and slower WFL growth. However, no associations from the LGMM models were statistically significant after accounting for multiple hypothesis testing. When assessing average lipid values across these latent class groups, most associations pointed towards the faster growth groups having more favorable lipid profiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study provides evidence of associations between infant growth from birth to five months and blood lipid profiles during adolescence. In each case, slower growth is associated with adverse lipid profiles - not faster growth as originally hypothesized. Further research with larger samples in this window of time can better distinguish the role of growth in early versus later infancy and childhood as an exposure affecting cardiovascular disease risk factors in adolescence.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Aim 3</title>
      <link>https://ann-von-holle.github.io/project/dissertation-aim3/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://ann-von-holle.github.io/project/dissertation-aim3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Poster presented at American Heart Association Epi|Lifestyle 2018 meeting. Slides created in 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.overleaf.com/read/ddyzyzrphshc&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Overleaf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early infancy serves as a window of time in which environmental exposures are associated with chronic disease risk factors in adulthood. Infant weight growth during this time has been associated with lipid levels in both animal models and observational studies in humans. Epigenetic modification is one mechanism explaining this association, which results in metabolic programming. Extensive studies support functional association between genetic regions and lipid levels. Infant growth may influence genetic mechanisms and subsequent metabolic programming of lipid metabolism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hypothesis&lt;/strong&gt;: Infant growth influences the strength of association between selected genetic variants and adverse lipid levels for children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aim&lt;/strong&gt;: Assess SNP-lipid additive association across latent early infancy growth classes for 20 candidate genetic variants underlying lipid metabolism and fasting lipid profiles assessed at average 17 years of age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Results&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Faster weight (pooled) and WFL (female) growth groups: positive association between rs72925845 and HDL-C.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HDL-C inversely associated with cardiovascular disease risk.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Expect negative association with HDL-C given established positive association with TG.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Faster weight growth group: inverse association between rs11076175 and LDL-C.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;LDL-C positively associated with  cardiovascular disease risk.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Expect positive association with LDL-C given established inverse association with HDL-C.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Faster growth appears to be protective against a few deleterious SNP-lipid associations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Heterogeneity of SNP-lipid association across growth patterns in this period suggests plasticity of response on a molecular level.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!-- Aim 3 of my dissertation examines the associations between lipid single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) and lipids conditional on growth classes. In this framework the growth classes function as effect modifiers of the SNP-lipid association. Both candidate lipid SNPs, chosen on the basis of marginal effects with adequate power, as well genetic risk scores will be covariates in the models. To characterize infant body size change,  I will use two analytic approaches as in aims 1 and 2: nonlinear mixed effects (SITAR) and latent growth mixture models (LGMM).
# 
# Our aim in this paper is to assess the importance of human growth during early infancy on lipid metabolism programming. We hypothesize that postnatal growth, serving as the exposure, has the potential to modify the association between lipid profiles and genotypes. We will categorize infant growth patterns from an infancy cohort using latent growth mixture models. Subsequent to categorization of growth patterns we will estimate additive genetic association with lipids across these latent groups to assess gene-environment interactions.
# This exploratory work can generate further hypotheses to inform future interventions aimed at unfavorable child growth patterns linked with chronic disease risk factors including dyslipidemia.--&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
